Welcome to the demo video
production tutorial!
Here I am going to describe
the process, tools, and resources.
So, where to start in the process
of making a video tutorial?
If you are a beginner,
it could be a frustrating moment—
from equipment to software—
but in this video, we will go
through the process step by step.
The ADDIE model is the process
traditionally used by instructional
designers and training developers.
The five phases of the model—
Analysis, Design, Development,
Implementation, and Evaluation—
represent a dynamic, flexible guideline
for building effective training
and performance support tool
such as video.
At the analysis stage:
Research the topic
that you will make a video tutorial for:
Who is the audience
and what are their characteristics?
For example, this video is for beginners.
Identify the outcome for the audience.
For example, as the result, users
will learn how to make a video tutorial.
What is the timeline
for project completion?
Plan to send your video
for the initial feedback
and to have enough time left
to resolve the issues before posting.
At the design phase, write a script.
You can use this template, I will
share it in the link below the video.
Design the user interface
and user experience:
colors, music/no music.
For intro/outro
use a color-blind-friendly palette.
For example, blue/orange,
blue/red, blue/brown
[are common
color-blind-friendly palettes].
Apply a visual design,
choose a professional-looking background
or a template for your video.
At the development stage,
you will need the equipment:
a laptop, a microphone, a quiet room,
professional background, and the look.
Recording:
Record sections of the video.
There are plenty
of screen recording tools.
In the link below the video,
you will find the document
with the list of free tools
and tutorials how to use them.
It’s important that free tools
don’t have watermarks,
recording limits, and have good quality.
There are options like using
Zoom to screen record
and Windows preinstalled software.
Editing: At the implementation stage,
trim, crop, and arrange
the clips/sections.
Sound: Re-record some sections
if there are sound issues
like sound gets too quiet or sounded
like the microphone is too far.
Sound is important
for the visually impaired audience.
There are free editing tools,
the full list is in the link
to the document below the video.
Subtitles: For short videos,
use YouTube automatic captions tool.
[Consider editing the result!]
You will find the links
to other subtitles generating tools
and guides how to use them
in the same document
in the link below the video.
You can also create your own captions.
SRT files for captions are preferable
because they are used on Facebook,
YouTube, and other platforms.
Make sure that captions are translatable!
[Evaluation]
Upload your video on platforms.
Write a description [to the video].
Receive the feedback,
resolve issues accordingly and publish
And here is the exercise:
Make a video tutorial
with translatable subtitles,
not more than 5 min long,
share with 3-5 people for their feedback,
publish on platforms!
Thank you so much for joining!